地          球          脉          动
远离一切陆地
Away from all land
海洋
the ocean.
地球表面多半被海洋覆盖着
It covers more than half the surface of our planet
至今海洋的许多地方我们还无法触及
and yet for the most part it is beyond our reach.
许多地方实际上很荒凉
Much of it is virtually empty
水之荒漠
a watery desert.
这里的生命被迫不停寻找食物
All life that is here is locked in a constant search to find food
在这广袤的大洋中只为获得宝贵的能量
a struggle to conserve precious energy in the open ocean.
无     垠     深     海
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
这是最大的鱼类
The biggest of all fish
30吨重,12米长
thirty tons in weight, twelve meters long
鲸鲨
a whale shark.
它的巨大身躯上是靠吃一种很小的海洋生物长成的
It's huge bulk is sustained by mere microscopic creatures of the sea
浮游生物
Plankton.
鲸鲨经常在它的最好的进食地点之间洄游
Whale sharks cruise on regular habitual routes between the best feeding grounds.
二月,鲸鲨从遥远的委内瑞拉海岸来到这片浅海
In February, that takes them to the surface waters far from the coast of Venezuela.
这里已经有访客了
Others are already here.
饵鱼(当饵料的鱼)因为同一原因来到这里 吃浮游生物
Baitfish have come for the same reason to feed on the plankton.
鲸鲨非常准时地到场
The whale shark has timed it's arrival exactly right.
奇怪的是,小鱼围着鲸鲨游
Oddly, the tiny fish swarm around it.
小鱼利用鲸鲨当盾牌
They're using it as a shield.
还有掠食性鱼类在附近潜伏
Other predatory fish are lurking nearby.
黄鳍金枪鱼(黄鳍鲔) 看上去比鲸鲨机灵多了
Yellowfin tuna. They seem wary of the giant.
鲸鲨开始下潜,离开这过度拥挤的地方
The shark dives, as if to escape from such overcrowding.
现在黄鳍金枪鱼开始进攻这没有保护的饵鱼
Now the tuna have a chance to attack the unprotected baitfish
而后,鲸鲨归来
but then back comes the giant.
鲸鲨张开大口,满嘴都是饵鱼
It has taken a vast mouthful of the baitfish itself.
浮游生物看来并不是鲸鲨的唯一食物
Plankton, it seems, is not the only food for a whale shark.
鲸鲨和金枪鱼一起享受这大餐
Both shark and tuna feast together
金枪鱼必须机警地远离鲸鲨
but the tuna must be wary.
除非它们想成为鲸鲨的腹中美餐
Even they can end up in the whale shark's stomach.
掠食者在这里想怎么吃就怎么吃
Predators here must grab what they can, when they can
因为好事不多,好景不长
for such events do not last long.
只有在水况非常好的情况下 才会出现这样的鱼群聚集
The dense shoals, on which so many depend gather only when water conditions are perfect.
许多掠食者把大部分的时间用在来回巡游
Many predators spend much of their time cruising the open ocean
寻找食物上
endlessly searching.
吃浮游生物的蝠鲼也是
Plankton feeding rays do so,
用最省力的方式在水中滑翔
gliding with minimum effort.
远洋白鳍鲨
The oceanic whitetip shark
也是节省能量的旅行者
another energy efficient traveler.
它擅长的是即使在最空荡的海域也能找到猎物
It specializes in locating prey in the emptiest areas of the open ocean
巡游高度在海平面至水下100米之间
patrolling the top one hundred meters of water.
鲨鱼能在水中“闻”到各种气味
Taste in water, is the equivalent of smell in the air.
白鳍鲨更是能跟踪细微的痕迹
An oceanic whitetip is able to detect even the faintest trace.
小小的引水鱼跟着它游
Small pilot fish swim with it.
鲨鱼比它们更容易发现猎物
The shark can find prey far more easily than they can
引水鱼就收集鲨鱼咬碎的食物碎片吃
and they'll be able to collect the scraps from it's meals.
它的长长的垂直的胸鳍
It's long, fixed pectoral fins
可以让它花费很小的力量在水里巡游
enable it to soar through the water, with the least expenditure of energy.
鲨鱼发现了一群香蕉鱼
This shark has found a school of rainbow runners.
这给了鲨鱼一个机会
It would eat one, given the chance
但是香蕉鱼游的敏捷迅速,白鳍鲨不容易捉到
but rainbow runners are swift and agile and not easily caught
因此鲨鱼耐心等候
so, it bides it's time.
可能到最后可以找到一条 容易抓到的老弱的鱼
There's a chance that, eventually, it may spot a weakened fish that's catchable.
猎人,还在无尽的等待着
The hunter
即使远离陆地也有刺激的事情
endlessly waiting.
一群多达500条的真海豚
Excitement far from land.
它们感觉到附近有食物
A school of dolphin five hundred strong.
开始加速追赶
They've sensed there's food around, and they're racing to catch up with it.
消息传开,大量的真海豚上路了
The news has spread. Now a number of schools are on their way.
它们向亚速尔游去 葡萄牙以西1000英里的火山群岛
They're heading towards the Azores volcanic islands a thousand miles west of Portugal.
海豚利用声纳扫描大海
The dolphin scan the water ahead with their sonar.
已经接近目标
They're close to their target.
这就是了!竹荚鲭
This is it. Scad mackerel.
单只海豚想吃它们是很困难的
It's difficult for a single dolphin to catch the fish.
为了避免浪费精力,它们进行团队合作
To avoid wasting energy the work as a group.
它们将鱼儿赶上海面,目的是诱捕它们
They drive the fish upwards, trapping them against the surface
因为那里还有掠食者在等着鱼儿们
and there, other predators await them.
猛鹱 正在等着海豚把猎物赶上水面
Cory's shearwaters. They're waiting for the dolphin to drive the prey closer to the surface.
猛鹱出动了 它们可以潜至20米甚至更深来捉鱼
Now the shearwaters can dive down on them, descending to twenty meters or more
海豚们锁定了从海面撤退的鱼群
and the dolphins block the baitball's retreat.
海豚吃饱后迅速离开了
The dolphins leave as soon as they've had their fill
最后,竹荚鲭也逃出了猛鹱的攻击范围.
and, at last, the mackerel sink below the diving range of the birds.
昼去夜至,海洋发生了另一个重大变化
As the Sun disappears, a profound change takes place in the ocean.
深海的浮游生物开始浮上水面, 另一支饥饿的部队准备接受这些猎物
Deep water plankton start to rise from the depths and another hungry army prepares to receive it.
如果环境适宜
Every night, wherever conditions are right,
每天晚上会有无数的深海生物到海面来觅食
countless millions of creatures from the deep migrate to the surface, seeking food.
一条小旗鱼
A baby sailfish,
仅15厘米长.边游边大快朵颐
fifteen centimeters long, snaps up everything in it's path.
再过3年,它将重达60公斤 成为海洋中强大的猎手
In three years' time, it'll be one of the oceans most formidable hunters weighing sixty kilos.
只是现在很弱小罢了
Just now, however, it's very vulnerable.
这种蝠鲼非常巨大
These manta rays are giants.
8米宽,超过2吨重
Eight meters across and weighing over two tons.
头部对称的2块刀片状的凸状物 帮助蝠鲼把浮游生物送到嘴里
The blade-like projections on either side of the head help to steer plankton into the manta's mouth.
黎明到来,浮游生物又回到深海
Dawn returns, and the plankton sinks back into the depths.
如果想要跟下去,必须乘潜水艇
If we are to follow, we must use a submarine.
随着我们在黑暗中不断下潜
As we descend into the darkness,
水压越来越大,温度越来越低
the pressure builds, the temperature falls.
在500米深处,新的神秘动物出现了
Below five hundred meters, new, mysterious animals appear.
它们奇异的外形帮助它们在漆黑的空间里悬浮
Their bizarre shapes help them to remain suspended in the dark space.
有一些貌似浅海生物
Some resemble creatures familiar from shallower waters
另一些则长相怪异
others defy classification.
周围全都是飘下来的有机颗粒
All around, organic particles drift downwards.
海雪是海洋表面上的生物产生的小型有机物碎屑
Marine snow, detritus from the creatures swarming in the sunlit waters above.
这场“雪”给这里的许多动物提供了食物, 比如这只蜘蛛蟹
The snow is food for many animals here, like the sea spider
与虾和螃蟹有一定的亲戚关系
a small relative of shrimps and crabs.
它的这些附肢样的奇怪的腿, 上面的羽毛可以防止它沉下去
Those strange leg-like appendages are feathered, to stop it from sinking.
它的腿也可以接住海雪
They can also enmesh marine snow
然后将挑选过的食物送进嘴里
which it wipes carefully into it's jaws.
一条锯齿鳗笔直向上, 静静地挂在水里
A sawtooth eel hangs upright and motionless.
向上凝视, 可让它在微弱光线的环境下发现猎物的影像
Gazing ever upwards, it watches for prey, silhouetted against the faint glimmerings of light from the surface.
它可以在这里挂好几天. 直到猎物近到让它可以发动攻击
Days may pass before prey swims close enough for it to strike.
随着下潜深度增加,周围已经一片漆黑
Farther down still, the blackness is complete.
没有阳光可以照射到这么深
No vestige of sunlight can penetrate as far as this.
食物非常缺乏
Food is very scarce
一点能量都不能浪费
and nothing can afford to waste any energy.
小飞象章鱼拍打翅膀来游泳
A dumbo octopus simply flaps a fin
不象它的浅海亲戚利用喷射水流的反作用力
no need for the jet propulsion used by it's shallow water relatives above.
这个奇异世界中的最神秘生物
The weirdest, in this world of the strange,
幽灵蛸,来自地狱的吸血鬼鱿鱼
vampyroteuthis, the vampire squid from hell.
它受到惊动就会稍稍后撤
Disturb it and it only retreats a little distance.
如果继续惊动它,就会看到它的特别防御
Go after it, and it has a special defense.
想看它要做什么,就要关掉灯光
To see what it does, you must switch off the lights.
吸血鬼鱿鱼可以自行发光
The vampire squid has lights of it's own.
它的足囊中的发光微生物发出的光可以迷惑敌人
Bioluminescent bacteria shine from pockets on it's arms to confuse it's predators.
这些是眼吗
Are those eyes?
实际上这些发光的触手末端用来吸引掠食者攻击 从而保护头部不受伤害
In fact they're spots at the end of it's mantle. A bite there, would leave the head unscathed.
威胁消失,吸血鬼鱿鱼也消失在黑暗中
The threat diminishes, and vampyroteuthis disappears into the blackness.
最终来到海床上
At last, the sea floor.
离海平面2英里
Over two miles down,
压强是地面的300倍
the pressure here is three hundred times that at the surface.
海雪落到这里也要好几个月的时间
It takes several months for marine snow to drift down as far as this.
当你越过满是岩石的海底陆地边缘 前面便是广阔的海底平原
As you travel away from the rocky margins of the continents an immense plain stretches ahead.
绵延几千英里
It extends for thousands of miles
逐渐向下蔓延
gradually sinking downwards.
海底泥中也有些微的踪迹
There are faint trails in the ooze,
证明即使在这里也有生命存在
signs that even here there is life.
这是其中一种
These are what made some of them
海胆,收集并过滤漂流物
sea urchins sifting the accumulating drifts.
虾用脚尖优雅地站着, 很挑剔的选择最吸引它们的食物
Shrimps standing on elegant tiptoe fastidiously select the particles that appeal to them
不过海底也和其他地方一样, 既然有吃素的,肯定有吃肉的
but, in the deep sea, as everywhere else if there are grazers, there are hunters.
一只安康鱼 肉眼几乎不能辨别躺在那里的它和沙子
A monkfish, almost indistinguishable from the sand on which it lies.
既然有引诱猎物过来的诱饵 何必浪费能量到处追赶猎物呢
Why waste energy chasing around, if you can attract prey towards you with a lure?
这个可能有点大
Maybe that one was a bit big.
安康鱼可以等好几天
The monkfish can wait, for days if necessary,
直到合适的猎物出现
until the right sized meal turns up.
食腐类动物则需要到处寻找食物
Scavengers on the other hand, have to move around to find their food.
蟹类可以从水里嗅到从上面落下的尸体的极细微的气味 并以此追踪到食物
Crabs can detect the faintest of tastes in the water and that helps them locate the latest body to drift down from above.
鳗鱼已经在这里进食
Eels are already feeding on the corpse.
等脚类动物,比如1/3米长的巨海虱
Isopods, like giant marine woodlice a third of a meter long
也在撕食腐烂的肉
are ripping into the rotting flesh.
在接下来的几个小时里, 这些食腐动物会尽情分享这份大餐
Over the next few hours there'll be frenzied competition between scavengers of all kinds to grab a share.
有时候,也有想不到的大好事
Just occasionally, there is a gigantic bonanza.
一头抹香鲸的尸体
The remains of a sperm whale.
约5个月前死亡
It died five months or so ago.
除了粘在骨头上的鲸脂外已经没什么东西了
There's little left but fatty blubber clinging to it's bones.
鲸鱼肉滋养了方圆几里的生物
It's flesh has nourished life for miles around
但现在盛宴快结束了
but now the feast is almost over.
宽达1米的蜘蛛蟹仍然在采集这最后的残羹剩饭
Spider crabs, a meter across, still pick at the last putrid remains.
再过几个星期,除了骨头外什么都不会留下
A few weeks more, and nothing will be left, but bare bones.
蜘蛛蟹必须尽快吃完.直到下一个畜体落下之前
The crabs will have to fast, until the next carcass drifts down.
不过不是所有的食物来自阳光普照的海面上
But not all food comes from the sunlit world above.
大西洋被一条无边的火山山脉劈成两半
The floor of the Atlantic Ocean is split in two by an immense volcanic mountain chain that winds unbroken
绕地球绵延45000英里
for forty five thousand miles around the globe.
在这里 海底裂缝中含有大量溶解矿物质的滚烫海水
In places, it's riven by great fissures, from which superheated water loaded with dissolved minerals
喷进冰冷的深海里
blasts into the icy depths.
硫化物冷却所形成的浓烟有3层楼那么高
Clouds of sulfides solidify into towering chimneys, as tall as a three story house.
400度的高温 剧毒的化学物质足可以杀死绝大多数生物
At four hundred degrees this scalding cocktail of chemicals would be lethally toxic to most forms of life
但是令人震惊的是 一种特别的细菌在这里繁荣昌盛
but astoundingly, a particular kind of bacteria thrives here
大量的虾又以细菌为食
and feeding on the bacteria, vast numbers of shrimps.
即使在没有太阳的能量驱动, 也会诞生丰富的共生动物群
So, beyond the farthest reach of the Sun's power a rich independent community exists,
并直接吸收从地心喷出的能量
that draws all it's energy directly from the Earth's molten core.
在地球的另一端,西太平洋和日本的交界处
On the other side of the planet, in the western Pacific bordering Japan
龙火山带
the dragon chimneys,
另一些在黑暗的海底喷发的火山口
another series of hot vents, erupting in the darkness.
这里更多的不同的细菌因为相同的原因而繁荣着
Here, more, but different bacteria thrive in a similar way.
在这里也有很多甲壳类动物 不过和大西洋的海底火山迥然不同
And here, too, more crustaceans, but quite different species from those around the hot vents in the Atlantic.
这些螯龙虾(属蟹类)
These are squat lobsters,
覆盖着有毛的甲壳, 互相争抢最佳位置
clad in furry armor jostling with one another beside the jets of superheated water
来摄取喷出的炙热海水中的细菌
for the best places, from which to graze on bacteria.
这种和大西洋相似的现象,相当于一个个绿洲
These vents, too, like those in the Atlantic are isolated oases
分布广泛,又各自独立
so widely separated, that each community is unique.
在太平洋的其他地方
Cross to the other side of the Pacific,
加拉帕戈斯群岛附近的海底, 还有另一个海底裂缝在喷射炙热海水
to the deep near the Galapagos Islands and there are yet other fissures venting superheated water.
距海面一英里半,一个叫北九地区的地方
One and a half miles down, at a site known as Nine North
高耸的火山烟囱滋养着引人入胜的巨大管栖蠕虫
towering chimneys support a spectacular display of giant tubeworms.
这些火山口带来的丰富的能源 甚至可以让这些蠕虫长到3米长
These vents give off so much energy that some of the worms reach three meters in length.
这是已知长的最快的海洋无脊椎动物
They're the fastest growing marine invertebrates known.
据统计,超过50种生活在这里的生物被发现
All told, over fifty different species have so far been found living here.
这些熙熙攘攘的生物群落
The inhabitants of these bustling communities
生长速度虽然很快,不过存在的时间也可能很短
may grow at speed but their existence can also be short,
因为火山口的喷发是不确定的
for the vents do not erupt indefinitely.
说不定突然间它们就会消失
Suddenly, unpredictably, they may become inactive.
9个月后,北九地区
Nine months have passed at Nine North.
火山口丰富的生物群现在 只剩下了寒冷贫瘠荒凉的遗址
What were only recently chimneys teeming with life have turned into cold, sterile mineral monuments.
地壳喷出的能量漩涡转移到了别处
Some eddy, deep in the Earth's crust diverted the volcanic energy elsewhere
整个微观世界也黯然失色
and, an entire microworld was extinguished.
在有的地方,火山喷发后会形成巨大的水下山
In places, volcanoes have erupted to build great submarine mountains.
据估计海底共有30000座火山
There are thought to be around thirty thousand such volcanoes
如果从海床开始算 甚至有一些比珠穆朗玛峰还要高
some, measured from the sea floor, are taller than Everest.
火山开凿出来的绝壁 一直延伸到山顶
Sheer cliffs soaring to drowned volcanic peaks.
带着海底养分的强大的洋流与海底山相接 便顺山而上
Powerful currents sweep up the mountains' flanks transporting nutrients from deep water towards the summits.
坚硬的岩石 给这些绚丽的共生种群提供了很好的停靠地点
The hard rock provides excellent anchorage for communities of great variety and stunning color.
几米长的软珊瑚
Soft corals, several meters across
收集流过它们身边的海雪
collect the marine snow as it drifts past.
海鞭在海流中伸出手来
Whip corals stretch out into the current.
大海绵从冰冷的海水中汲取营养
Giant sponges filter nourishment from the cold water.
一个丰富的物种群落在这里昌盛
A richly varied community flourishes here
得益于洋流持续不断地携带养分从这里流过
sustained by the nutrients and detritus in the icy currents that flow around the peak.
这些生物在这座死火山的的繁荣地点, 离阳光照射到的地方还有1英里呢
Yet it is all blossoming on an extinct volcano, a mile below the reach of the Sun.
鹦鹉螺
A nautilus.
白天它躲在400米深的海底
It spends it's days hiding four hundred meters down
到了晚上,它就游上来 到珊瑚礁附近寻找食物
But as night falls, it ascends up to the reefs, to look for food.
它那优美的外壳由充满空气的小室组成
It's graceful shell contains gas filled floatation chambers,
使它可以控制深度
that control it's depth.
它的动力来自虹吸管喷射的水流
It's powered by a jet of water, squirting from a siphon
由于它是倒着游 所以它自己也很难看清楚自己要去哪里
but it travels shell first, so it can't see exactly where it's going.
它是已经进化到已经没有壳的章鱼和乌贼的近亲
It's nearest living relatives are squid and octopus which, over evolutionary time, have both lost their shells
章鱼也已经成为了猎食鹦鹉螺的主要天敌
and the octopus has become one of the nautilus' major predators.
章鱼,伪装的大师
It's a master of disguise.
鹦鹉螺必须远离它们
The nautilus keeps well clear of them.
它的小触手有非常灵敏的化学感觉器, 可以探测到敌人和猎物的踪迹
It's small tentacles carry highly developed chemical sensors which can detect traces of both predators and prey.
鹦鹉螺利用喷水器挖沙子
It uses it's water jet to dig in the sand.
因为它游泳耗费的能量极少, 所以只需每个月吃1顿饭
Because it devotes so little energy to swimming, it only needs a meal once a month.
得到什么东西了
Got something.
如愿以偿. 黎明快到了所以它必须回到深海里去
And just as well. Dawn is approaching and it has to puff it's way back, to deeper waters.
30英里外的海上, 大量的鱿鱼游到海面上
Thirty miles away, shoals of squid are jetting upwards towards the surface.
晚上,鱿鱼寻找浮游生物和小鱼
By night, they seek small fish among the plankton,
不过它们必须谨慎
but they're cautious.
太平洋花斑原海豚
Pacific spotted dolphin.
它们靠声纳导航
They're guided by their sonar.
海豚经常团队合作
The dolphin, as so often, are working as a team,
协同攻击,来迷惑敌人
synchronizing their attacks to confuse their prey.
黎明来临, 鱿鱼,鱼和浮游生物再次下沉隐没在黑暗中
As dawn approaches, squid and fish and plankton retreat downwards, to shelter in the darkness.
有一些成为孤岛的火山高耸在海床上达9000米 几乎快要到达海面了
Some of these isolated volcanoes rise as much as nine thousand meters from the sea floor, reaching close to the surface.
这里的日照非常充足
Around these peaks invigorated by daily sunshine
海洋中的生物在这里大量繁荣
marine life flourishes in spectacular abundance.
鱼类在这里大量汇聚的原因是 火山迫使洋流把海底的养分送上水面
Fish crowd here, because the volcano forces nutrients to the surface
使得浮游生物十分旺盛
encouraging the plankton to bloom.
海洋流浪者翻车鱼来到海边让珊瑚鱼给它打扫卫生
An oceanic wanderer, a mola mola stops by to be cleaned by reef fish, at the sea mount edge.
蝴蝶鱼排成一队忙着吃翻车鱼身上的线体寄生虫
Butterfly-fish pluck string-like parasites from it's flanks.
翻车鱼以超过1000米深的深海水母为生, 那里的水温比这里低20度,
The huge fish lives on jellyfish over a thousand meters down where the water is twenty degrees colder
翻车鱼可以在下次深海攻击前上来暖和一下
so, a brushup near the surface, allows it to warm up before making more deep water forays.
这个火山已经处于海面之上
The summit of this volcanic mountain rises above the surface of the sea.
阿森松岛
It's Ascension Island
距最近的大陆800英里
eight hundred miles from any other land,
长途旅行者们生死攸关的避难所
a welcome vital haven for long distance travelers.
军舰鸟可以在海上持续待几个月
Frigatebirds spend months continuously airborne at sea
不过到了筑巢的时候 它就从海洋各处飞回到阿森松岛
but at nesting time, they come to Ascension from all over the ocean.
一个充满了火山灰和火山岩的不毛之地
The island's barren slopes of volcanic ash and lava
却提供了一个筑巢的好地方
might seem to offer perfectly good sites for a nest
不过军舰鸟要挑选偏僻的地点
but the frigates choose an even more isolated site
水手长鸟岛 阿森松岛旁边的一个偏僻小岛
Boatswain Bird Island, a lonely pillar, just of Ascension's coast.
阿森松军舰鸟是世界上最轻的海鸟之一 翼展特别长
Frigates are the world's lightest bird, relative to their wingspan
它们只需要很小的付出就能在海上飞行好几个星期
and they can soar for weeks on end with minimal effort.
相对于地上拥挤的巢穴, 在天上飞就悠然自得多了
They seem much more at home in the skies, than in a crowded colony on land
不过筑巢是必须的
but nest, they must.
它们从大西洋各处飞来,全部聚居在这个岛上
They come from all over the Atlantic to this, their only colony.
这里还有憨鲣鸟
There are boobys here, too.
为了生儿育女 全世界的海鸟们才来找这种偏僻的小岛
To raise their young, seabirds worldwide seek such remote islands.
水里游的也来这个阿森松岛繁殖
Swimmers also come to Ascension to breed.
一只雌性绿海龟正在靠近岸边
A female green turtle approaches the coast.
它已经有两个月没有吃东西了
She's not eaten once, in two months.
因为她从1000英里外的进食地赶来
She may have traveled one thousand miles from her feeding grounds
她的最伟大的旅行
the greatest journey of her kind.
还有其他的绿海龟
Many others are here, too,
正在有沙质海床上休憩, 等待黑夜的降临
resting on the sandy sea floor awaiting the darkness of night,
这样可以较安全爬上沙滩
when it'll be safer to visit the beaches.
几周前下的蛋,在这个季节伊始
Eggs that were laid a few weeks ago, at the start of the season
开始孵化了
are beginning to hatch.
多数的蛋是在夜间孵化
Most hatchings happen at night.
现在是白天,小海龟们很容易受到攻击
Now, in the light of day, the young are extremely vulnerable.
它们必须尽快爬向大海
They must get to the sea as soon as possible
不过小海龟的试炼才刚刚开始
but their trials have only just begun.
许多小海龟淹死在巨浪中
Many will drown in the pounding waves.
在接下来的20年时间里
During the next twenty years,
大多数的海龟将不可避免的死去
the vast majority will inevitably die
活下来的海龟最终还会做它们的母亲做过的事情
but those that survive will, eventually, as their mothers did before them,
回到它们孵化过的海滩上繁殖
return to the very same beach where they were hatched.
它们如何从1000英里外再次赶回
How they find their way back across thousands of miles of open ocean,
仍然是个谜
we still have no idea.
军舰鸟正在高飞
A frigate soars.
水下某个地方一定有食物
Somewhere, beneath the surface below, there is the food it must have.
可在哪里呢?
But where?
飞越海洋的鸟类必须懂得寻找食物的踪迹, 不然就意味着死亡
Those that fly above the ocean must be able to read the signs of fresh supplies, or perish.
距墨西哥海岸100英里,
A hundred miles from the Mexican coast,
军舰鸟锐利的眼睛正在搜寻
and keen eyes have spotted movement.
3米长的旗鱼正在接近猎物
Sailfish, three meters long, are closing in on prey.
它们只用恰到好处的力量来猎杀
They will only use just enough energy to make their kill
从不贸然浪费力气
never wasting a fin stroke.
近100条旗鱼的包围了这群饵鱼
Nearly a hundred sailfish have surrounded a single school of baitfish.
很少能见到上百条的旗鱼在同一个地方出现
It's very rare to see so many of these hunters in one place.
旗鱼张开大大的背鳍来把猎物赶到一起
To herd their prey, the predators raise their huge dorsal fins.
旗鱼不恰当的攻击会严重伤害到同伴
A mistimed strike by one sailfish, could fatally damage another
所以每条旗鱼不断变换颜色 从蓝色--有斑纹--黑色
but each continually changes it's color, from blue, to striped, to black
这可以警告同伴注意, 同时也可以迷惑饵鱼
that warns it's companions of it's intentions and also confuses the prey.
当饵鱼被赶上海面的时候
As the shoal is driven nearer the surface,
又进入了海鸟的攻击范围
it comes within the range of the seabirds.
在这片空旷的海域中 这些小鱼无处可藏
Out here, in the open ocean, there is nowhere for the baitfish to hide.
旗鱼的生活很费能量
Sailfish live a high obtain life.
为了生存,它们必须每天寻找猎物
To survive, they must find prey daily
所以它们终生都在奔波
so their entire existence will be spent on the move.
海洋占据着地球上90%的生存空间
Over ninety percent on the living space for life on our planet, is in the oceans
是现存的最大动物
Home to the biggest animal that exists
也是史上最大动物的家
or has ever existed.
蓝鲸
the blue whale.
有的重达200吨
Some weigh nearly two hundred tons
体积是最大的恐龙的2倍
twice the size of the largest dinosaur.
撇开体积不论, 我们仍然不知道它在这广袤的海洋中去哪里旅行
Despite their great size, we still have little idea of where they travel in the vast oceans
也不知道它们去哪里繁殖
and none at all of where they go to breed.
这地球上最大的动物只有一种主食
The largest animal on Earth feeds almost exclusively
一种非常小的甲壳类动物-磷虾
on one of the smallest krill, shrimp-like crustaceans.
它们一口可吃进几吨的海水 然后再过滤出想要的东西
They take many tons of water into their ballooning throats in a single gulp and sieve out what it contains.
每天一头蓝鲸可以吃进400万条磷虾
Every day, each one swallows some four million krill.
这样巨大的食量依赖富饶的海洋的不断提供
Such gargantuan harvests depend on the continuing fertility of the oceans
但是全球环境的变化 让蓝鲸赖以生存的浮游生物急剧减少
But global changes now threaten the great blooms of plankton on which the whales depend.
曾经在不久以前
Once and not so long ago
30万头蓝鲸让海洋看上去充满生气
three hundred thousand blue whales roamed the oceans
现在,只有不足9000头
now, less than three percent of that number remains.
我们的星球仍然充满惊奇
Our planet is still full of wonders.
当我们探索奇迹的时候 我们所谋取的不仅仅是去了解它,而是征服
As we explore them, so we gain not only understanding, but power.
掌握在我们手里不仅仅是鲸的命运和未来
It's not just the future of the whale that today lies in our hands
还有这个生命星球上所有生命的存亡
it's the survival of the natural world in all parts of the living planet.
要么灭绝它们, 要么关爱它们
We can now destroy, or we can cherish.
这取决于人类自己
The choice is ours.